This is CS 50 week 2.
we're excited to have like a little group here,
so feel free to drop questions in the chat.
Um,
hopefully this will be an interactive session,
so I'm gonna be asking you guys for
some input and
and you can feel free to ask questions as well.
So,
Let's get started.
So I'm Kelly.
If you haven't seen me before,
I'm the preceptor here at Harvard,
so I run
the college,
uh,
class on campus here.
That's my email if you ever
want to contact me.
And so this week,
week two,
we got
more in depth on C.
and so some of the questions that
that in lecture David addressed and some
questions that you might still be thinking about
are
what steps are involved in compilation.
So how does
code
turn from source code
to
what actually runs?
When should we use arrays?
What are strings?
And what's the point of command line arguments?
What are these things?
What's the difference between
a standard input?
And then finally a question that you might be thinking about
as you write your code
is what makes for good design?
What does
design mean?
And as you may know,
design is one of the axes that we grade for and so what are we looking for
when we think about good design?
So we're gonna start with that point
and I'm gonna ask you all
what you think are
some characteristics of good design
in code.
So feel free to write in the chat what do you think
good design means?
Simple,
easy for someone else to read,
not for boast,
yeah,
so is it helpful for someone else?
Can they understand what's going on in your code?
Is it efficient?
Is it simple?
Yeah,
yeah,
these are great.
So some of the things that we came up with
that you can think about when you're writing your code,
first question is,
is your code
efficient?
Yeah,
no,
don't repeat yourself.
So as the slide says,
we wanna avoid unnecessary repetition
and redundant operations.
So
you should avoid copying and pasting your code
even if you're making slight changes and that usually should be a sign
if you're doing some copy and pasting
perhaps this is a good time for you to consider using
loops or abstractions using a function
to try to hide away some of that repetition.
And then with redundant operations
if a variable is computed multiple times
that can be also a sign that maybe you should consider storing this variable
in
storing this value in a variable so that you're not
repeatedly computing the same thing over and over again.
Another question you can ask is,
is your code easy to maintain?
So if your problem gets bigger
and bigger,
is your code going to be easy
to keep up
with the scale of
what you're working on?
So
two things to think about here are prototyping your functions.
So as a reminder,
this is when
you're declaring
potentially a helper function,
so a function that's helping you solve the problem you're doing.
And taking that first
prototype,
the first line that declares this function
and declaring it
above your main function.
And so
it's easy for other humans to read and it keeps your main code at the top
and so that's helpful.
Another thing we would like to note is to avoid magic numbers.
So
what does that mean?
Magic numbers
we think of as hard coded numbers.
So
these numbers that might be might seem a little bit
arbitrary and their value will not change throughout the program.
And so if that's the case we encourage you to use
constants to define that as a constant.
For example,
something you might do in this week's problem set
is use
the fact that
the alphabet has 26 letters
and so
over the course of your program,
the alphabet is not suddenly going to add more letters
and so that is a number 26
that might be good to define as a constant
rather than just
simply typing in 26.
So to
sort of reinforce some of these ideas we're gonna play a little game.
I'm gonna show two
pieces of code
and I'd like you to put in the chat which one do you think
is better
and why do you think that?
So I take a second to think about that and read the pieces of code here.
Yeah,
so I'm seeing people
are saying the second option,
option B,
is better.
Someone says A.
Yeah,
so
the difference here
we can see is that
in option A
in this conditional check we're checking is I less than
the length of
some string.
Option B,
we're declaring
this length of the string sterling
um
as N
and then the conditional check is I is less than N.
And so
We would prefer option B in this scenario
because we don't have to perform this
string length computation every time we run this loop.
If we kept it as option A,
we'd be doing a lot of unnecessary computation
because we have to get the length.
We're asking every single time
how long is the string?
How long is the string?
When,
when you run this loop,
it's not necessarily going to change lengths.
All right,
so how about
this
example here?
So you have option A and option B.
All right,
yeah,
so I'm seeing a lot of people say option A.
So as we see here
talking about magic numbers,
option A declares months in a year equals 12 as a constant integer
and so
like someone said in the chat here,
the number of months in a year
are not gonna change
throughout the course of your program
and so
having that defined as a constant
is arguably better design.
Than having just a 12 in your code where
someone reading it might not know what that means.
So this is a good example of avoiding magic numbers.
OK,
how about
this
example?
So we have 2
if statements here.
OK,
yeah,
so I'm seeing some people say A.
Does anyone want to
make a guess as to why
A might be a better option here?
One less line of code.
It's redundant to ask else,
yeah,
so that that's exactly right.
So
in these
two options.
We see option A.
We have,
we're checking if some expression is true.
If that's true,
let's return a success,
otherwise we'll do
uh return status code of one.
And the other option,
option B,
we're still checking that expression,
but in the case
that the expression is not true.
We're also adding an ES case here,
but the ELS
case,
as people are saying,
is redundant
because you're not gonna reach that,
um,
in any other case
and so
no matter what we're gonna be returning one and so it's,
it's not necessary to have that
extra case.
OK,
how about this next one?
So this is also.
A conditional.
Which
flows better,
which makes
which one's better designed.
OK,
yeah,
so I'm seeing a lot of people say B.
And why might that be?
It's more succinct,
if false,
exit immediately,
yeah,
so.
What's going on in in this program
is that
we have some
bullying
that's storing either true or false,
and
we wanna check if
that is true.
If success is true,
we're gonna like do a lot of
code
we're gonna run a lot of things.
If it's not true,
then we might have some.
Exit case like
you should just stop the program immediately.
And so
adding that as a guardrail at the beginning before you have your
lots of code
is
arguably like easier to tell what's going on here
um and because
it is a little bit more succinct here we're avoiding
that extra ES case.
OK,
great.
So I just want to pause here if anyone has any questions about design,
what we're looking for in design,
any of those scenarios.
OK,
alright,
so let's get into the actual,
oh,
question.
So we only need to use Ls when we have more than 2 possible answers or options.
Yeah,
so it'll depend on the code that you're running,
but
you can think about whether or not adding this ELS case is gonna be redundant or not.
So
is the code within your ELSE block
going to run.
In
either case,
like
if you had the ES block or if you didn't,
so that's sort of a good way to tell.
But
thank you for the question.
OK.
Anyone else?
OK,
feel free to drop more questions in the chat and
we'll move on to the content of this week.
First of which we're talking about arrays.
So
as an example,
some of you may know this game Pac-Man
or have seen a leaderboard like this on a video game
and so
if we were making a video game of our own here and we wanted to store
the top 5 scores of our players.
So far the only way we know how to do this
is by declaring like 5 integers maybe
score 1 score 2 score 3,
score 4 score 5,
but that is not necessarily going to be
the best way to do this,
right?
It's a lot of variables to keep track of
and
um it's not
super well designed,
it's a little sloppy,
right?
And so.
Arrays that we introduced this week
are a nice way of
of categorizing or storing these items together
so you might imagine that we have an array
like this
that stores our top 5
scores in Pac-Man.
So if I were to try to actually declare this array,
how do I make this array,
you might write a line,
a line of code that looks sort of like this.
So we have in
scores,
square brackets 5.
And so what is this actually composed of?
First we have the name,
so we have a name of the array,
this case called scores.
We also specify the
number of items we're gonna have in this,
uh,
array,
which in this case is 5.
And then we also have to specify the type,
so what are
the items gonna be?
What,
what type will they be?
So in this case integers.
OK,
and so that's how I declare like an empty array.
We don't have any values in it.
How might I,
uh,
update this with say our
first,
uh,
score,
our highest score.
So that might look something like this,
right?
So
arrays are 0 indexed,
meaning that
the first thing in the array
we call the index 0
and then index 1234,
and so on.
So if I wanted to set the first
highest score to 120,
I would write a line of code like so that says
the name of the array,
so scores
at the index of 0.
We're going to set that equal to 120.
And so similarly
if I wanted to update the next highest score,
it would be scores
at the index of 1 equals 86
so so on and so forth
we can fill up our entire array
if you knew all 5 ahead of time,
this is another way of doing so so you can
immediately declare
the array scores
with its five values in curly braces like so,
and that would
set up your array.
Like
this.
OK,
if I have this array
and I wanted to say print them to the screen so we're like showing the leaderboard,
we might have a 4 loop like so.
So
I've set up my array of scores
like so and then
I've set up a 4 loop
that starts at 0
and goes up to 5,
which means it's gonna repeat 5 times,
which is the amount
of scores we have
and then for each repetition we're gonna print
the
placeholder
of an integer
and have scores at the index of
I.
So what's going on there?
Well,
you can think of the first time
this 4 loop repeating I is going to equal 0
and so on that first iteration we're gonna print out
scores at index zero,
which is like the first score of 120
and then on every subsequent
iteration I is gonna go from 0 to 11 to 2,
and then print the next item in the array.
So that is
one way that we can print out the items that are in our array.
OK,
any questions about arrays,
working with them,
declaring them?
Updating values.
Alright,
feel free to drop
them in the chat if you do.
We'll move on to strings.
OK,
what if you don't know the size of the array and want it to be updated by user input?
That's a great question.
And this actually
will be something that we address in a coming week,
um,
but
one way to do so could be actually that you just
ask the user first you get the size,
and then you declare the array
so you
so that you actually know
that length arrays are always dynamic.
So
if you have experience with Python,
it is a little bit different.
Um,
Python's like
lists versus sees arrays.
Um,
when you declare an array in C,
that's the length that it's gonna be like that's the memory that's allocated,
um,
you can't necessarily change that,
but
in coming weeks we're gonna learn about another data structure that is dynamic.
You can add
more things to the end of it and change that length.
Some great questions.
What's the difference between an array and a list?
Does he use lists?
C does not use lists.
And you can actually we'll talk about this
in Python Week when we see those differences,
but
um C uses arrays.
Those are,
you know,
static.
They're not gonna be changing lengths.
Uh,
Python does use lists which are a little bit different because
they're a little bit more
dynamic,
um,
but you'll hear more about that
in Python.
OK,
so
we'll move on to strings,
which.
Oh,
do they support multiple data types?
No.
So that's actually a good question.
In
an array,
every single item in that array,
the element
has to be of the same data type,
which is why we,
when we declare an array,
state that very explicitly,
like in
scores
square bracket 5,
right?
That's gonna be 5
integers
in an array.
Great question.
OK,
so we'll move on to strings.
Strings,
as,
uh,
we heard in lecture,
are actually not a key word
that are in C natively,
right?
So
this like string,
um,
variable type is actually ACS 50
provided
training wheel per se,
um,
before we actually dive into what that is.
But one thing we did learn is that
just like an array,
a string can actually just be thought of
as
an array of characters,
so in this case if I have the name Emma.
The way you can think about it
as an array
name is actually gonna just be these
five
characters,
right?
So E M M A
and then what is that backslash zero?
Does anyone wanna put that in the chat?
What's that for?
No,
yeah,
exactly,
so
that backslash 00
indicates the end of your string.
So
when it's stored in memory,
you know exactly where that string is ending.
So in the same way that
strings are arrayed
just like arrays,
we can actually
index into them
to get certain characters.
So if I wanted to get
specifically the first letter of this string,
I can do the same square bracket notation to index
and get the 0th index.
So in this case,
name square bracket 0 would get us E.
Why we put and why do we put the end
on the string so the null character is helpful because
um
just so that when it's in memory or if you're working with strings
if you encounter the null character,
then you know that
the string has finished,
that the string
is,
that's the end of the string.
Good question.
OK,
and so similarly,
if I wanted to get the second
character,
I would do name at index 1
and so on.
Any questions about
more questions about strings and how that works?
OK.
All right,
so we're going to put this into practice a little bit.
Um,
it is NUL,
yes,
NUL,
I believe.
Yeah,
good question.
OK,
so we're gonna start out with this exercise.
If you're watching this asynchronously,
I encourage you
to pause here and give this a try for yourself,
um,
but we're gonna walk through
this.
So
this
exercise character by character,
we wanna write a program called Printtsy
that takes a string as input from the user
and then prints it character by character.
OK.
So I moved to the terminal.
OK,
oops.
I'll restart my
code space here.
What are the operations that can be performed using strings?
That's a great question,
so.
As we'll talk about very shortly,
strings
and each character within them,
the character
is also represented as,
um,
can be represented as a number,
right?
So capital A
on the ASCI tables is equivalent to
A or 65,
yeah,
and so.
You can do these sorts of operations where you
add
say
to 65 and represent that as a character
and that will be B
and so
we're gonna actually do this in a following exercise but let's start out here.
We're gonna
hide this away.
I'm gonna start by coding print.
Oops.
OK,
we're gonna start by coding print.c.
It's
and we're gonna include some libraries to start with.
So what are some libraries that I know I'm gonna use
um.
I know that I'm gonna be using Get string,
which is in CS50.H,
so I'm gonna include that.
I also know that I need standard IO yeah.
Standard IO.
H.
And
I also
know.
Actually,
yeah,
we'll,
we'll start with those two,
and then I'm gonna do Ain't Maine Void
here.
And so first off I want to start by asking the user for some input.
So I'm gonna do string
text.
Equals get string and then.
Ask for
some input here.
All right,
and so once I get
this text variable.
How am I going to print it out
character by character.
So if I'm doing it character by character,
what?
Might I use
To do something repeatedly.
A loop.
Yes,
thank you.
OK,
but what kind of loop?
That's the question.
So we could do a 4 loop.
We could do a Y loop.
OK,
so people are saying 4 loop.
Yeah,
let's do a 4 loop.
So for
And I equals 0.
And then what is this 4 loop?
How many times it's going,
how many times is it going to repeat?
Depends on
the user's input,
right?
So how do I get the length of
The string that the user is going to input.
Sterling,
yes.
Yes,
OK,
great,
so I can use
sterling,
which is a function
that is actually in string.h.
So I also need to make sure that I include that up here
before using it.
So this is going to go up to the length of
The text
and then each time increment.
Great,
and then for each
iteration,
I wanna print out.
What am I printing out here?
If I want to do character by character,
yeah,
percent C,
which is the format code for a character,
great,
and
that will be a placeholder for
my
character
within
the text,
right,
so.
Which index am I going to do here?
Yeah,
people are saying text at index I.
so that I is going to iterate each time.
Someone asked about including the.
Backslash and
what might that do stylistically
you think about.
I can also show you,
yeah,
OK,
that's gonna put each character on a new line exactly,
yeah,
if I included this backslash N
rather than seeing
like
if I put Kelly,
my name,
we would have
K on one line,
then E on the next line,
L,
and so on.
So let's start by making this print.
Dot slash print
I put in my name.
Yeah,
so if that,
if I include the backslash and then it prints it out on each line.
Right,
as someone's saying in the chat.
If I want a new line at the end of printing it out,
I should include.
A backslash and here
instead.
So let's
make print again.
Dot slash print.
Great,
so we've printed out what the user has given us.
Any questions about this exercise,
feel free to put them in the chat.
So before we move on to the next exercise,
I do want to take a second to look back at our print.c program
and ask if we're noticing any design improvements that could be made
because this program does work,
it's correct,
but
like we were talking about design earlier,
there are always ways that we can make this maybe
happen a little bit more efficiently.
So,
one thing you might notice here
is within our for loop,
we're comparing I is less than ster length of text.
And so the Stirling function is being computed
every single time we run
the for loop.
But is that number gonna be changing while we run the for loop?
Probably not.
That text length is just gonna be a static number.
So
one way we can improve this design
is by
setting the length to its own variable.
And this will be computed at the beginning of the 4 loop.
And then each time we perform this comparison within the for loop,
we're just comparing to
this new variable that I call Ln.
And so
this way
we're reducing some of that computation
and this program will run just a little bit more efficiently.
So if you have any questions about that,
feel free to drop them in the chat.
But now we can move on to
reverse.
C,
which is going to be similar to the last one,
but with a little bit of a
spin on things.
So,
we're going to write a program,
reverse.c that takes an input
as a string and then reverses it.
So the first letter becomes the last letter,
the second becomes second last,
and so on.
So I'm gonna go back
to my ID
and I'm going to code reverse.
C.
And since
this program is going to be pretty similar to the last one,
I'm just gonna copy and paste,
print that C here and use that as a base.
So what
is gonna be different about reverse.
C
rather than print?
We know we want to print it backwards.
So
what line of code might I want to change here?
Yeah,
so this 4 loop.
Right now we're iterating
I starting at 0 and then
until the length of the text.
But maybe it makes sense for us to reverse that,
so.
Rather than starting I at 0,
maybe I'm going to start it
at
the length of the text.
And then instead of incrementing,
maybe I
decrement.
And I want I to stop
when I get to the 0 with the character
so I can do.
Keep iterating until I is greater or equal to 0,
but are there any issues with this?
So setting I to sterling
text.
So let's say I have
an input of
the word cat that's 3 characters long.
This is gonna give me
3.
But
as we know,
because of zero indexing.
That is actually not gonna be within the string itself.
I'm actually gonna get the Noel character which
um we talked a little bit about
which looks like that backslash zero,
but that's not gonna print anything.
And so I actually want to start
this loop at ster length of text
minus 1,
so that it starts
at the end of my string rather than
beyond it
at that null character.
So let me try this out.
Gonna make rivers.
Dot slash reverse.
And then
maybe I'll put my name again.
Great.
And then we see it going
Y L L E K in reverse,
just like we wanted to.
All right,
so we've done these two exercises,
um,
drop in the chat if you have any questions about either of them,
but
we'll continue from here.
So working with strings a little bit more
if you recall
each of the letters that we work with
by the ASCI table that was decided by
some humans many
time
a long time ago
I declared
these numbers to be equivalent
to these letters
and so because they have these numerical
representations
we can actually do some.
Like operations
and
checking things using these
numbers and so one example of that.
Might be with
so Emma for example the string here
actually
can be written out
as this array of integers.
And so why is this helpful information to know?
Let's try
seeing that in this exercise.
So we're gonna write
a program called Alphabetical
that prints out yes
if a lowercase strings characters
are in alphabetical order,
no if they are not.
So right off the bat here.
How
do I know
if something
is in alphabetical order?
Say if I got
a lowercase A and lowercase b.
How would I know that these two things?
In order
are alphabetical,
yeah,
so someone says if X is less than Y.
As we saw with this chart.
B
has the value of 98,
which is greater
than
A's value of 97.
So we can take that piece of knowledge into this exercise
and come up with a way
to check.
If our string is in alphabetical order.
So I'm gonna start
coding alphabetical.c.
And then
Before
I'm also gonna.
Let's just build on this
prissy.
OK,
so the first part is the same,
right?
We're asking for an input here,
but now we're not gonna be printing out
anything,
uh,
within this loop,
but we do wanna check
whether something
whether the characters are in alphabetical order.
So like a few people have said here
we're gonna be checking
the ASCI value we're gonna be comparing it.
So,
let's see,
I can do an if statement.
And then what might this condition look like here?
Let's say if I want to check the first letter
against the second letter.
Or perhaps what is,
how do I get
the first letter of
this text variable.
Yeah,
text I
text or text 0.
Great,
so
0 index would get us the first letter.
And of course because we're doing this within a loop
that's great we're starting with
I equal to 0
and so we want to check if that's less than.
The next letter,
which is gonna be I plus
1.
OK.
So if this is true.
Then
what?
If it's if these two characters are in alphabetical order,
then
what should I be doing?
Print no so we wanna print no if it's not in alphabetical order,
yeah,
so we're not really doing anything
if
this is true
and so when we have cases like this it might be good to think
like
how can I restructure this
maybe to
change.
This
or this condition.
So rather than checking if it is in alphabetical order,
maybe we check if it's not in alphabetical order.
Right,
so if this
is greater than
the the next letter.
Then we already know that the rest of the
string is not going to be in alphabetical order
so we can print F.
No
And then just
finish
this program,
Return 0.
Yeah,
exactly
OK.
So if we loop through this entire
string
and we're checking
each
two letters one by one,
which if they're in alphabetical order
and we get through the entire string.
Then we know
that yes.
If you've gotten to this line 17
and you haven't returned
the program,
then we can say yes,
it's in alphabetical order.
OK,
so let's test this out and see.
How it goes,
so.
Uh,
length.
OK.
OK,
so I'm gonna do ABC.
Not in alphabetical order.
Why might that be happening?
Text I + 1 will not exceed the string boundary,
yeah,
so
just to show this more visually
if I print out.
Print off.
The
character or maybe the integer version.
Of
Um,
text
I.
And then at index
1 + 1.
We can see like what
values are actually being compared here,
so let's make this again.
ABC oops.
OK,
Yeah,
so we see these are the first two
that we're checking A and B.
That's in alphabetical order.
The next two A and and S by
by accident,
um,
but that's still in alphabetical order.
But then it's checking
S and then 0,
which in this case if anyone remembers what,
what's this 0.
Referring to
the null character,
yeah,
exactly,
and the null character at the end of the string is what it's comparing it to,
so we know that we're going a little bit too far in our comparison
that we should actually just stop
here.
So we can say.
Finish or continue running this
as long as I is less than length minus 1 so it it
repeats one less time
than before.
So let's try this again.
ABC,
yes,
and I can remove these print statements now that I'm done
debugging,
OK.
So our last portion
is talking about command line arguments.
So what are some examples of programs that we've seen
that take command line arguments?
Cow say,
yeah,
exactly
from lecture
cow program so that takes some arguments
also.
Things that you've been doing this past week make Mario
Mario in this case is a command line argument make is the command.
Same with
when I run something
this is something you might encounter this week
where you actually provide the
program that you're running
some input in this case 13.
So this is no different than the functions that we've seen before,
right?
When we had
this calculate quarters function from cash,
it takes in
a function argument
which is
an integer that we call cents,
and then it specifies the type that we're returning.
So in this case it returned
how many quarters
that we had.
Similarly,
we have
in Maine void that we've been seeing a lot
and so up until now we've used void
as this input argument.
It means it's not taking anything in
and then it's returning an integer
which
like in lecture we talked about yesterday
that is the exit status that signals like
if it ran successfully like a 0 or if it ran into some
error.
So now
rather than taking in no input
we can try experimenting with
including some command line input and so
that's what this looks like
we have in arc,
which is like the count of the arguments,
how many arguments were put in,
and then an array of strings
that's that has the actual
um
commands that were
put in the
in the terminal.
So a question that might come up for you is like why are we even doing this?
Why not just use get it or get string?
So
Any
thoughts on this in the chat?
Why might you prefer to do it,
do something with command line arguments,
yeah,
it saves time.
Yeah,
so you can think about
if I were running
make Mario
instead of
running
with a command line argument,
uh,
say you had to type in like
it asks you,
um,
what program are you trying to make
when you run make
so it saves some time.
Yeah.
Great,
so
this is what
those arguments are actually gonna look like here
if I run Make Mario and Terminal above,
then we're gonna have a string
array
called RV
that contains the,
the string make and then the string Mario,
and then an argument counter variable which has the count of that
array
which in this case is 2.
Same thing if we had something like slash Caesar and then 13.
So that has
dot slash Caesar
as the first string and then 13 as the second string.
OK,
so now let's say we're gonna make a program called Initials that takes
the some person's name,
in this case my name,
and then spits out
the first,
uh,
character of each
giving us like the initials in my case KD.
Well,
with RV
we know that
RV 0 is gonna be this dot slash initials
string and then RV1 gives us
my first name Kelly,
and then
RV2 gives us
ding.
And then because these are strings we also know that if I wanted to get
the actual letters within that
string.
I can do RV at index 1,
which is Kelly,
and then
at index 0 it's the first letter which is K and then similarly with
D.
OK,
so any questions about command line arguments?
What would RC be?
Great question.
Anyone else in the chat wanna answer that?
What would RGC be in this scenario?
3,
yeah.
Yeah,
so
dot slash initials is 1,
Kelly is 2,
Ding is 3,
so we have 3 arguments.
OK.
So let's move on to this final exercise.
Why does it count from
one?
Yeah,
great question.
So RXC is
giving you a count of how many
arguments there are
rather than
when we talk about counting from zero.
It's usually like an index
in an array.
And so
rather than saying so the array still has 3 elements inside of it,
which is why RXC is 3 in this case.
But
when we're actually doing the indexing,
the first is called 0 index.
Great,
OK,
so let's do this final exercise.
Write a program initials.c
just like we saw
that takes the name as an input
and then outputs their initials,
so we're gonna accept them as command line arguments
and assume that names will be separated by space.
OK,
so let's move over here,
clear my terminal
and code initials.c.
OK,
so I know I'm gonna need some libraries here.
So if you got age for.
String
since we know we don't have string.
And standard IO.h.
OK.
We might need some more,
but we can always come back.
So I'm gonna start with in main
and then instead of void here I know I'm
gonna be taking in some command line arguments.
So I'm gonna have an arg C
and then string arg.
The
OK.
So.
I know that I'm gonna be needing
the string in each
um command that was inputted.
So I should probably do a loop,
right?
What should my loop
start at?
Say
I'm given.
Dot slash initials.
Kelly Dang,
right,
so let's say this is my input.
If I want to loop over just this,
these two.
Strings
What should it start at?
My for loop.
RB 1,
yeah,
so this is RB 1,
this is RB 2.
So let's start this
actually at one.
And then
loop as long as I is less than.
What should it be looping until
3,
yeah,
so it could be 3.
I also specified,
you know,
and maybe I actually put my middle name in here.
Now this is.
So what
variable captures like this
the number of arguments we're gonna have.
OK.
I'll give it to you for free here RC.
So RGC as a reminder is the number of
arguments.
It's like count.
So in this case it would be 4.
In this case it would be 3 and so it changes dynamically,
which is what we want here rather than me just
saying it has to be 3.
Some people have multiple middle names maybe you know,
so you wanna capture
um
different scenarios.
OK.
So now that we have um
this
looping over each
part of the name.
How do we print out the first letter of that name?
So what should I print out here?
Possible inn equals arc.
Yeah,
so you could do that.
Um,
but if you're not,
if you
You don't necessarily need
to save RCC as its own variable as it's already
a variable.
OK,
yeah,
people are saying RVI at index 0.
Great,
so I'm gonna print out a character.
And that character
is going to be.
Hard to be
At index I
And position
0.
Great.
So let's try this
out here.
Dot slash initials.
KD great.
I wanna start it on a new line just for stylistic purposes.
Let's just add
a new line there.
Oops,
OK,
make,
yeah,
and then.
Great.
OK,
what if now
I
did initials and then just didn't give it any input?
It just prints out nothing,
but
I might wanna actually handle that right and tell the user
you're supposed to give me
some input.
So how might I check that here?
Use an if,
yeah,
so I should check like.
Did this person input any arguments?
How might I do that?
Say I want them
to have input it at least.
Yeah,
so if RCC is less than 2,
meaning
they either didn't
put any
arguments after dot slash initials,
um,
or they have nothing,
which is not really the case here,
but.
Right,
so if this is not lessened or if it is less than 2,
then we should just say.
The correct usage of this program is initials.
And then like your first and last name.
And then we should just return one
signify
there's an error.
So
let's make again.
And run
OK,
great,
so now rather than printing out nothing,
it actually gives us
this
error message here.
OK,
let me make one last time.
And try this,
but
David's name?
DJM.
Great.
OK,
awesome.
So any questions on
this program?
Some people were saying yeah.
RC does not equal 3.
Yeah,
we could do that too.
That would just mean changing,
um,
let's say
for
this case then it wouldn't work
since we have 4 arguments.
Yeah,
yeah,
so these are all design decisions that
you as a programmer are gonna
programmer are gonna be thinking about when you're writing
your program.
OK.
Awesome.
OK,
so that's all of the content for this week.
Thanks for your participation.